A Guide to the Papers of Mark Twain, 1862-1946
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series VI: Charles L. Webster & Company Debt Receipts
  - A. Howard Ritter to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 March 25; TLS, 1 p. (Box 10)
    Requests date Parker & Scudder was sent $12.90 payment from Charles L. Webster & Company.
  - A. P. Herrington, Richmond, VA, to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 March 26; ALS, 1 p. (Box 10)
    Cover letter for return of $6.54 sent him by mistake.
  - E. O. Vaile to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 March 26; TL[S], 1 p. (Box 10)
    Has received last 2 payments for Charles L. Webster & Company debt but not one on May 18 1897; has searched records thoroughly.
  - Armand P. Herrington, Chattanooga, TN, to Katherine I. Harrison with ALS conveying appreciation, 1898 April 2; Receipt (Box 10)
  - A. Howard Ritter to Katherine I. Harrison with TLS cover letter, 1898 April 2; Receipt (Box 10)
  - Asa Bird Gardiner, for Irene Rucker Sheridan for estate of Philip H. Sheridan, to Katherine I. Harrison with receipt, 1898 April 4; TLS, 1 p. (Box 10)
  - Elizabeth Bacon Custer to Katherine I. Harrison with ANS cover letter, 1898 April 10; Receipt (Box 10)
  - J. S. Hand to Katherine I. Harrison with ALS cover letter, 1898 April 16; Receipt (Box 10)
  - Katherine I. Harrison, New York, to Bainbridge Colby with AN 1898 June 3 Bainbridge Colby to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 May 20; TLS, 1 p. (Box 10)
    Asks if he has any more information on P. J. White. AN 1898 June 3 Bainbridge Colby to Katherine I. Harrison says he knows no other way to reach P. J. White.
  - The Forum Publishing Company to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 June 3; Receipt (Box 10)
  - E. O. Vaile to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 June 4; Receipt (Box 10)
  - Oscar H. Marsh to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 June 6; TLS, 1 p. (Box 10)
    Received one check but not the other.
  - "Persons From Whom Receipts in Full Have Been Received" with A additions, [1898 July]; T List, 2 p. (Box 10)
    List of creditors of Charles L. Webster & Company who have returned receipts.
- Autograph book of Daniel Terrance Mulvey, containing Mark Twain's signature 1906-1907 (Box 10)
  Mulvey, a page in the United States Senate, collected the signatures of many Senators as well as that of visitor Mark Twain.
- Photographs of Mark Twain (Samuel Clemens) and Family (chronological)Photographs of Mark Twain (Samuel Clemens) and Family (chronological) (Box 11)
  [1868] 2 items 1. Photograph of Mark Twain, standing between Josh Billings (on the left) and Petroleum V. Nasby (on the right), by H.G. Smith of Boston, cut into oval shape; with note from Frank E. Bliss to unknown correspondent, scribbled on an envelope, about the ownership of the photograph (6314-q) [1870s] 2. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking left, in a dark suit, oval with sepia tone [Prints01144] (6314-q) [1872 Sep] 3. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing left, by Charles Watkins of London; autographed “Yours Truly, Samuel L. Clemens, Mark Twain” on reverse [Neg 4x5-1591-c, Prints09879] (6314-q) [1873] 4. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking left, by Gurney of New York, brown tone [Prints09882] (6314-q) [1873] 5. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking left, by Gurney of New York, brown tone; taken from Ellen B. Stuart Album of Historical Figures (7055) [1877-1878] 6. Photograph of a photograph of Olivia Clemens seated between Susy (on the left) and Clara (on the right), by Franz Hanfstaengl of Munich, Germany [Prints09889] (6314-j) 1881 Feb 12 7. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right, oval with sepia tone by Warren’s Portraits of Boston; inscribed, “To Miss Koto- With kindest regards of hers truly, S. L. Clemens, Hartford, Feb 12, 1881” (PS1316.A1 1882 C.5) [1884] 8. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right; signed “truly yours, Mark Twain” [Neg 4x5-1591-d] (6314-q) [1884] 9. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated, facing right, in a white suit with sepia tone [Neg 4x5-393] (6314-q) 1884 10. Photograph of Mark Twain with George Washington Cable, both standing, one hand in pocket, sepia tone, signed by both men, taken by Sarony of New York [Prints09853] (6314-p) 1884 11. Photograph with of Mark Twain George Washington Cable, both standing, one hand in pocket, sepia tone, signed by both men, taken by Sarony of New York, damaged (6314-q) [post 1890] 12. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated in his study, in a dark suit with crossed legs, holding a cigar, by Pach Bros. of New York [Neg 4x5-392, Prints09884] (6314-q) 1893 2 items 13. Photograph of Olivia L. Clemens, full body, facing left, sepia tone, by Eddowes Bros. of New York [Prints09885] (6314-q) 1893 14. Photograph of Olivia L. Clemens, full body, facing forward, sepia tone, by Eddowes Bros. of New York [Prints09886] (6314-q) 1895-1897 36 items 15. Photographs, black and white, of 1895 train trip from Cleveland to Vancouver, B.C. by Clemens family (Mark Twain, Olivia, and Clara) with James B. Pond. Photographs from the Clemens’ London home in 1897. Includes notes by James B. Pond on reverse. [Neg 4x5-888-j, Neg 4x5-394-a, Neg 4x5-1590, Neg 4x5-1590-a, Neg 4x5-888-k, Neg 4x5-888-n, Neg 4x5-888-m, Neg 4x5-888-l] (6314-t) 1895 16. Large photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking right, sepia tone, by Sarony of New York {OS Box L-7} (6314-p) 1895 Sep 17. Photograph of Olivia L. Clemens, head and shoulders, looking left, sepia tone, by The Falk Studios, Melbourne; signed “very truly yours, Olivia L. Clemens” (6314-q) 1896 Jan 24 18. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking left, sepia tone, by The Falk Studios, Melbourne; inscribed “To Mr. Parday, in memory of a very pleasant day in Bombay. Sincerely yours, SL Clemens (Mark Twain)” [Prints09865] (6314-q) [1896-1897] 19. Photograph of Mark Twain, full body, facing left, in suit with top hat, by Alfred Ellis of London, originally mounted with 3 others (folder 1 of 4) [Neg 35-79, Prints01140] (6314-p) [1896-1897] 20. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing left, in suit, by Alfred Ellis of London, originally mounted with 3 others (folder 2 of 4) [Neg 4x5-394-a, Prints01143] (6314-p) [1896-1897] 21. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated, looking left, in suit with top hat, by Alfred Ellis of London, originally mounted with 3 others (folder 3 of 4) [Neg 4x5-394-b, Prints01142] (6314-p) [1896-1897] 22. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing forward, in suit with top hat, by Alfred Ellis of London, originally mounted with 3 others (folder 4 of 4) [Neg 4x5-888-b, Prints01141] (6314-p) 1897 Jun 2 items 23. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated, facing forward, in a suit, by Alfred Ellis of London, with Mark Twain’s signature; done especially for J. B. Pond, Twain’s agent {OS Box L-7} [Neg 4x5-888-h] (6314-p) 1898 May 16 2 items 24. Photograph of Mark Twain, black and white, head and shoulders, looking right, by J. Löwy of Vienna; inscribed with “truly yours, Mark Twain” [Neg 4x5-888-g, Prints01145] (6314-q) 1900 25. Photograph of a oil portrait of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing forward, by James MacNeil Whistler, with Whistler’s butterfly signature (6314-x) [1900s] 26. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing forward with sepia tone, by Newsboy of New York (6314-q) 1900 Apr 6 4 items 27. Photograph of Mark Twain, sitting by window, sepia tone, by H. Walter Barnett of London, inscribed with “ To Sir William Des Voeux with warm regards of S. L. Clemens and the same from Mark Twain” [Prints09892] (6314-k) 1902 28. Photograph of Mark Twain, framed in dark frame, seated, facing forward, in a dark suit, by Taber Photograph Co., signed at bottom by Mark Twain {back wall behind book stacks} (6663) [1902 Jun] 29. Photograph of a photograph of Mark Twain with Laura Hawkins Frazer, Twain’s inspiration for Becky Thatcher in The Adventures of Tom Sawyer [Prints09891] (6314-j) 1904 2 items 30. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated, facing forward, in a suit, by Apeda Studio of New York [Neg 4x5-888-f, Prints09855] (7267) [1906] 31. Photograph of Mark Twain, in bed, wearing white, reading a magazine [Prints01147] (6314-q) [1906-1910] 32. Photograph of Mark Twain with Dr. Edward Quintard, the family doctor; signed, “sincerely yours Mark Twain” at bottom {OS Box L-7} (6314-p) [post 1907 Jun 26] 33. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated on porch, wearing academic costume, woods in background [Prints09867] (6314-q) [post 1907 Jun 26] 34. Photograph of Mark Twain, standing on porch, wearing academic costume, house in background [Prints09869] (6314-q) [post 1907 Jun 26] 35. Photograph of Mark Twain, standing on porch, wearing academic costume, woods in background [Neg 4x5-1591-b] (6314-q) 1907 2 items 36. Photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing forward, in a white suit with sepia tone, by A.F. Bradley of New York [Neg 4x5-888-e, Prints09887] (6314-d) [1907] 37. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated indoors with book, wearing white suit [Neg 4x5-1591-a, Prints09877] (6314-q) [1907] 38. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated on rock with kitten, wearing white suit [Prints09861] (6314-q) [1907] 2 items 39. Photograph of Mark Twain, standing indoors beside window, wearing white suit, holding pipe [Neg 4x5-888-c, Prints09860] (6314-q) [1907] 4 items 40. Photograph of a photograph of Mark Twain, seated indoors with book, wearing white suit [Neg 4x5-888-a] (6314-j) [1907] 2 items 41. Photograph of a photograph of Mark Twain, seated indoors with newspaper, wearing dark suit [Neg 35-81-b] (6314-j) [1907] 1 item 41a. Photograph print from the original Mark Twain glass plate negative taken in England showing Twain seated in his Oxford robes. Standing next to him is Frances Nunnally, one of the "angelfish" in his "Aquarium Club." (6314-aw) [1908 Jan] 2 items 42. Photograph of Mark Twain, playing billiards, brown tone [Neg 4x5-888-d] (6314-q) [1908-1910] 43. Photograph, playing cards with Clara Clemens [Neg 4x5-888-i, Prints01146] (6314-q) [1908-1910] 44. Photograph of Mark Twain, seated at piano, with Clara Clemens and Miss Nicol [Prints09862] (6314-q) 1909 Oct 6 45. Photograph of Mark Twain at Wedding of Clara Clemens to Ossif Gabrilowitsch: (left to right) Mark Twain, Jervis Langdon, Jean Clemens, Ossif Garbrilsowitsch, Clara Clemens, Rev. Dr. Joseph H. Twitchell; by Frank J. Sprague (6314-q) 1909 Oct 6 46. Photograph of Mark Twain at Wedding of Clara Clemens, standing outdoors, wearing academic consume [Prints09864] (6314-q) 1909 Nov 16 47. Framed photograph of Mark Twain, writing in bed, in dark wooden frame; includes letter to Vice President Zoheth Freeman and two plaques, one of the letter and one of its importance {OS Box F-9} (6314-ar) n.d. 48. Photograph of Mark Twain, profile view, in a photograph album in the papers of Walt Whitman (3829-t, Box 5, Folder 35, page 12) n.d. 49. Photograph of an unidentified girl, possibly one of Mark Twain’s daughters, 3 views, by Webster Art Gallery of Oakland, CA (6314-q) 1859-1894 5 items 50. 16 Prints of photographs at various ages, in various poses (6314-q) 1871 2 items 51. Print of etching of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking right, by W.H.W. Bicknell [Prints09883] (6314-q) 1877 52. Print of etching of Mark Twain, seating between Clara (on the left) and Susy (on the right), by W.H.W. Bicknell [Neg 4x5-888-p, Prints09880] (6314-q) 1883 Jan 5 53. Print of a photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right, oval with sepia tone [Prints09868] (6314-q) 1884 3 items 54. Print of a bust of Mark Twain, by Karl Gerhardt, one signed by Mark Twain (6314-q) 1884 55. Print of a photograph of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right, in a white suit, printed signature [Prints09881] (6314-q) [1884] 56. Print of a photograph of the Clemens family: (left to right) Susy, Mark Twain, Jean, Olivia, Clara; on the porch of their Hartford, CT home [Prints09890] (6314-j) 1891 2 items 57. Print of a portrait of Mark Twain, seated, facing forward by Elson of Boston, one signed by Twain (6314-q) [1894] 58. Print of a photograph of Mark Twain originally by Sarony, by N.Y. Photogravure Co., head and shoulders, facing forward (6314-q) 1895 Aug 22 59. Print of a photograph of Mark Twain, facing forward on a rustic porch, captioned “Announcement Without Words,” signed “truly yours Mark Twain” (6314-p) 1898 2 items 60. Print of an oil portrait of Mark Twain originally by Spiridon, head and shoulders, facing right, one signed by Twain (6314-q) 1899 61. Print of a oil portrait of Mark Twain originally by Spiridon, head and shoulders, facing right, in Portrait Series No 283 in The Book News Monthly [Prints09863] (6314-q) 1899 2 items 62. Print from a photograph, head and shoulders, looking right, by Elson of Boston, one signed by Twain (6314-q) 1905 63. Print from watercolor portrait of Mark Twain entitled “Mark Twain Pilot,” at helm of riverboat, “American Humor,” in Life Magazine [Prints09854] (6314-q) 1906 Sep 64. Prints of photographs of Mark Twain in rocking chair, wearing a white suit, with a commentary on moral progress by Twain [Prints09870-09876] (6314-q) 1906 Sep 65. Framed prints of 8 photographs of Mark Twain; 7 in rocking chair, wearing white suit, with commentary on moral progress by Twain; 1 shooting billiards in white suit with Albert Bigelow Paine {OS Box F-1} (6314-aa) 1934 66. Print from portrait of Mark Twain, by Frank A. Nankiwell, head and shoulders, facing forward, signed by artist (6314-q) n.d. 67. Print from etching of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking right (6314-q) n.d. 68. Print of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing left, printed signature [Neg 35-82-a] (6314-q)
- Clippings of Mark Twain (Samuel Clemens) and Family (chronological) (Box 12)
  [1897 Jun] 1. Clipping of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing left, originally from a photograph by Ellis of London, formerly with a card from Twain to J.R. Osgood and Co. (6314-j) 1898 Oct 2. Clipping of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing forward, originally by Marceau of Boston [Prints09866] (6314-q) 1903 Nov 2 items 3. Clipping of Mark Twain from series, “Three Famous Authors Outdoors” in Ladies Home Journal: “Mark Twain at Quarry Hill Farm,” “Even Mark Twain Sometimes Nods,” “Mark Twain and an Old Family Friend,” and “Mark Twain and His Porcelain Cat” (6314-q) [post 1904] 4. Clipping of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking right, originally by Walter Barnett; captioned “Mark Twain: Born November 30, 1835” (6314-q) [1906 Feb] 5. Clipping of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, looking right in a suit, by Florian; in the center of clipping, “Mark Twain’s Loving Tribute to His Wife” (6314-q) 1907 6. Clipping of a print of a stereograph of Mark Twain, standing with a pipe, originally by Underwood and Underwood (6314-q) [1907] 2 items 7. Clipping of Mark Twain, seated, in a white suit, in carved armchair with sepia tone [Neg 35-82, Prints09888] (6314-d) 1910 8. Clipping of Mark Twain, seated, facing right, originally by Histed; captioned “Mark Twain, died April 21st” (6314-q) n.d 9. Small clipping of Mark Twain, seated, facing forward, in a dark suit (6314-j) Postcards of Mark Twain (Samuel Clemens) (chronological) 1906 10. Postcard of Mark Twain, color, lying in bed, with caption “Mark Twain’s Muse” [Prints09878] (6314-q) 1906 2 items 11. Postcard of Mark Twain, lying in bed, smoking [Neg 4x5-888-o] (6314-j) 1906 12. Postcard of Mark Twain, lying in bed, writing (7267-a) n.d. 3 items 13. Postcards, featuring a photo of Mark Twain along with a quotation from Pudd’nhead Wilson or Following the Equator (6314-ay) Artwork associated with Mark Twain (Samuel Clemens) (chronological) 1859 Apr 9 photo 14. Photograph of pilot’s certificate issued to Mark Twain (6314-ae) 1899 bust 15. Bronze bust of Mark Twain, facing slightly left, on wood pedestal, inscribed with Mark Twain across lower front, by A. Weinert; back of the bust marked “The Henry Bonard Bronze Co. Founders N.Y. 1899;” with one photograph {left alcove of reading room} (6314-p) 1906-1921 engrav 16. Engraving of Mark Twain in profile by Bernhardt Wall, signed by artist [Neg 35-204-g] (10602, Item No. 6) 1906-1921 photo 17. Photograph of engraving of Mark Twain in profile by Bernhardt Wall [Neg 35-204-g] (6314-n) 1935 medal 18. 2 Centennial Medallions of Mark Twain by Kilney; sculpted relief facing right inscribed “Samuel Langhorne Clemens, Mark Twain Centennial 1835-1935,” “Kilney” on bottom left; mounted together on black velvet. With photograph of medallions. {OS Box O-2) [Neg 4x5-1608-b] (10602, Item No. 18) 1935 medal 19. Centennial Medallion of Mark Twain by Kilney; sculpted relief facing right inscribed “Samuel Langhorne Clemens, Mark Twain Centennial 1835-1935,” “Kilney” on bottom left, and “Robbins and Co, Attleboro” on back. With scanned copy of medallion. {OS Box AB-1, cell AD} (6314-n) [1970s?] photo 20. 4 photographs of places associated with Mark Twain: “Mark Twain Museum, Hannibal, Missouri;” “Mark Twain’s mother’s bedroom, Hannibal, Missouri;” “Cardiff Hill, Hannibal, Missouri;” “Jervis Langdon, owner of Quarry Hill Farm, Elmira, New York;” stamped “Life Photo by Dmitri Kessel; Mark Twain’s America” {OS Box L-7} (6314-ab) n.d. plaque 21. Clay plaque of Mark Twain and George Washington Cable, by Karl Gerhardt, inlaid with velvet {OS Box R-3} (7267, UVA Art Item No. 85) n.d. engrav 22. Color engraving of Mark Twain, framed, facing right; with inscription, “Truth is the most valuable thing we have. Let us economize it. Truly yours Mark Twain.” {OS Box F-1} (6314-aj) n.d. engrav 23. Engraving proof of Mark Twain, head and shoulders, facing right, engraving by Timothy Cole after a portrait by Abbott Henderson Thayer, with print of Mark Twain’s signature (6314-q) n.d. painting 24. Oil painting of Mark Twain, seated facing slightly left, cigar in left hand, with watch chain, by Mrs. Edward Ward, in heavy gold frame. With photograph copy. {back wall of reading room} [Neg 4x5-534] (6314-p) n.d. sketch 25. Pen and ink caricature of Mark Twain as a yachtsman by Harry Furness, signed by the artist (6314-q) n.d. sketch 26. Pen and ink sketch of Mark Twain, facing left, by Ben Morse, signed “Sincerely yours Mark Twain” (6314-j) n.d. photo 27. Photograph of drawing of Mark Twain in flames above an urn (6314-j) n.d. print 28. Print of a caricature of Mark Twain, by “Spy” in Vanity Fair Magazine [Neg 4x5-833] (6314-q) n.d. sketch 29. Watercolor caricature of Mark Twain, by Fudge, smoking a cigar {OS Box F-1} (6314-aj) n.d. plaque 29a. Bronze Wall Plaque of Mark Twain, sculpted by “F.E.C.” (6314-m) [stacks, Range L.1] Illustrations of Mark Twain’s (Samuel Clemens’) Works (chronological) [1867] drawing 30. Pen and ink drawing of woman combing her hair by an unidentified artist from “Concerning Chambermaids” in The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County and Other Sketches (6314-av) 1889 drawing 31. “Three Years After the Battle,” pen drawing by Daniel Carter Beard from A Connecticut Yankee in King Arthur’s Court {OS Box L-7} (6314-p) [1897] print 32. “The mate’s shadow froze to the deck,” print by Arthur Burdett Frost from Following the Equator (6314-q) 1898 drawing 33. “Buckstone was training with the rum party,” pen and ink drawing by Edward Windsor Kemble from Pudd’nhead Wilson {OS Box W-2} (6314-av) 1899 drawing 34. “The Assembly Was Dispossessed [Dispersed],” black and white wash by B. West Clinedinst from Roughing It. With negative copy. {OS Box L-7} (6314-q) 1899 drawing 35. “The Bathers at Leuk,” black and white wash by Thure de Thulstrup from A Tramp Abroad. With negative copy. {OS Box L-7} (6314-q) 1899 drawing 36. “The Caravan,” black and white wash by Thure de Thulstrup from A Tramp Abroad. With negative copy. {OS Box L-7} (6314-q) 1899 2 prints 37. “Flies, Dan’l, Flies!” by Frederick Burr Opper from Sketches Old and New (“The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County”), one signed by artist (6314-q) 1899 print 38. Pen and Ink print of Huck Finn in a Dress with Jim in Background, by Edward Windsor Kemble from Adventures of Huckleberry Finn (6314-q) 1899 painting 39. “Tom Sawyer’s Aunt,” black and white oil painting of Aunt Polly, by J.G. Brown, from The Adventures of Tom Sawyer {back wall behind book stacks}[UVA Art Item No. 77] (6314-ad) 1899 drawing 40. “An Unexpected Acquaintance,” black and white wash by Thure de Thulstrup from A Tramp Abroad. With negative copy. {OS Box L-7} (6314-q) 1905 Dec 21 drawing 41. “I am the Dauphin, the rightful King of France,” ink and watercolor drawing of the older of the two swindlers by W.A. Rogers from Adventures of Huckleberry Finn (6314-q) [1906] drawing 42. Pen and Ink illustration of starry night sky by Lester Ralph, from Eve’s Diary (6314-q) [1935] drawing 43. Watercolor and Ink illustrations from Slovenly Peter, translated by Mark Twain, by Fritz Kredel (6314-q) n.d. print 44. Colored print of an American tourist in Middle Eastern market by C.D. Weedon from Innocents Abroad, signed by the artist (6314-q) n.d. drawing 45. Ink and Watercolor drawing of Huck Finn and Jim, by F. Richardson from Adventures of Huckleberry Finn; autographs on drawing include Mark Twain, Dan Beard, Bayard Jones, A.W. Drake, C. Word Blaisdell, A.B. Wengell, Edwin B. Child, and others (6314-q) n.d. print 46. Print of a couple kissing by Seymour M. Stone from an unknown work, signed by the artist (6314-q) n.d. print 47. Print of etching of riverside scene with cotton bales, two boys, and a steamship by Edmund H. Garrett, possibly for The Adventures of Tom Sawyer or Adventures of Huckleberry Finn, signed by artist (6314-q) n.d. print 48. Print of kitchen scene with black man, old man, woman, and two boys by Arthur Burdett Frost, possibly for The Adventures of Tom Sawyer or Adventures of Huckleberry Finn (6314-q) n.d. 7 prints 49. Print of Mark Twain leaning against a column reading an inscription by Peter Newell from Innocents Abroad, signed by the artist (6314-q)